hello everybody so I wanted to give a
little introduction to the person we a
dialogue with today a couple days ago at
this point
Leo Ferraro so I met Leo Ferraro through
John berbay key and he's worked with
John and I think was as I think he
mentioned he was a student of John
Verbeck II like you know years and years
and years ago when he was in college
but since then they've had worked
together and they've wrote they've
written a bunch of different papers and
chapters two books one is irrelevance
meaning and the cognitive science of
wisdom now there is relevance
realization and the neuro dynamics and
neuro connectivity of general
intelligence flow as spontaneous
thoughts insight and implicit learning
and reformulating the mindfulness
construct the cognitive process at work
and mindfulness hypnosis and mystical
States some sexy title title is there
you know it's interesting this is
reading this this is a you know these
are pretty heavy heavy topics kind of
technical heavy topics as I'm reading
them however it's
interesting because the dialogue that we
had I found Leo to be incredibly
personable and even beyond personable
kind of speaking the wisdom that these
these titles point to but with a kind of
street smarts or something we ended up
talking a lot of a lot of this dialogue
ended up being about love I kept
circling back to love but not love like
some romantic sense of the word is like
some kind of feeling that comes and goes
and you know in the romantic sense the
word but more a embodied and acted
relational love that comes through in
how one sees someone when they're a
teacher especially we talked a lot about
a lot about being a teacher in his
experience of being a teacher his
experience of being a parent and and
what that's meant for him and how
they're connected and what's behind that
so um I really enjoyed my conversation
with him I'm it's gonna be the beginning
of many and I think I hope you enjoy too
so as Leo likes as Leo told me
afterwards he likes to talk and
apparently he finds me incredibly easy
to talk to so I'm breaking this video up
into two parts because it was just it
was a you know over two hours long and
also I think I may be doing that in the
future with a lot of dialogues I've
gotten a lot of feedback that you know
these hour and a half or an hour and the
40-minute conversations is just looks
daunting for people so I think I'll
probably just release videos that are
longer from now on in two parts and just
see how that goes okay couple house look
at just also to let you know um a lot of
you have written and asked me about this
so I will just announce it to everybody
the main course that I teach the the art
of circling which I you know I created
and teach and co-teach and co-create
with Mike with
like my own cofounders of my company
which is a deep dive into the heart of
circling and it's like a year long and
it's so if you're interested hit the
link below I think that there's
information down below and that's coming
up in March so let me know if you want
to talk about that you just click the
email and they'll be bubbly ways to
contact people for information about
that also I've been asked about just
working with people one on one if you're
interested in that just email me my
emails below as well all right thank you
enjoy with a recording at all yeah the
you know it's interesting I I'm it's
it's it's it's fascinating to me
so you just hopped on we've never met
right until now and like you stuck on
the screen and we're already talking
about kids and talking about like the
you know the like it's really it's it's
treacherous to try to decide to have
kids it was for me and like you know
even after you you know you have three
and even after you like having one to
make a decision to make no it's no more
it's no easier but you know you back
like looking back John and I were just
talking about this actually it's like
looking back when you look back it looks
like it's a straight line right ahead
like what that wasn't the experience at
the time but in retrospect you're like
oh yeah
obviously it's destiny or it's whatever
word that we use for that periods well I
mean everything is a straight line after
right I mean you've you you've you've
made the you've developed right you've
changed in such a way that now these
things are sensible to you and whatever
so it's the that's the end of history
illusion right that's why we don't think
we're gonna change Yeah right there's
everything so linear up to now there we
go like this is all predictive let's see
how much we changed
it's I don't know like all I know all I
can say is that for me the decision
hinged on looking at it looking at my
life yet my wife my wife and realizing
that of all the things that I've done in
my life everything I've done in my life
the thing I do best is being a dad and
by far the best thing I've ever done is
be a dad ah
hands down that's and and and why
wouldn't I do it more you know I mean I
think it's a it's a it's a it's a
powerful feeling for me like it's funny
because I said I always I never thought
I was gonna be that guy who had kids at
all right and I think that there's a
certain amount of weirdo individualistic
romanticism that infects us basically
guys in this regard you've got this you
know I'm a little wolf I can't be tamed
blah blah that's nonsense and and we're
very good at constructing idealized
fantasies of self-sufficiency and and
you know going on your own and being
like it's so much of what were raised
with in terms of manhood is about that
it's about being a problem solver and of
this and a handler things and we're
really oddly don't recognize enough or
don't appreciate enough our paternal
instinct as anything other than some
sort of like you know like badge or
stamp yes I was here I Pro created this
many times whatever but the act of
fathering of being a father it's the
same way that I wouldn't have imagined
having kids back years ago I now can't
imagine not being at that I can't
imagine not having been a teacher I mean
these are just such basic pieces of who
I am
of course I was gonna have more kids I
think this you know what seems like a
fraught decision at one hand
no no like of course like this is who I
am you know the best compliment I was
ever paid by another person was actually
by John and we taught together at a at a
private school and it it's funny because
I mean there's lots of things that that
people would like to be complimented for
there's lots of things that you know and
and and I'm you know I'm not lacking in
vanity or or concede or any of these
things and and and so you would think
that the the the best compliment I would
have received would be likely oh you're
such a badass or you're so smart or
whatever but John says because you know
what this is the thing that amazing at
you is you love better than anyone else
I know not that's a really powerful
thing to hear because it it's John was
was able to say that thing which I guess
made concrete something I've thought of
her hadn't grappled with explicitly yet
but that the thing that I have to offer
the thing that I give is not not
academic it's not you know as a teacher
it's not even the the say the
domain-specific knowledge that I'm
imparting but what what I do in how I
make I guess in the shelter I give my
students and in the sort of the yeah the
shelter is the best word I can think of
right now there isn't I don't know if
there's if this is mostly a flaw in my
vocabulary not the English language
let's be real but its but that thing
that that people don't really teaching
is an incredibly misunderstood thing
like an incredibly misunderstood thing
as a profession as a process all of it
like people really don't understand
teaching or teachers and even good
teachers even some of the best teachers
don't understand what they're doing I
mean not to be I'm not trying to be
disrespectful but I guess not everyone
is predisposed to understand the process
like one of the reasons why I studied
philosophy among other things is because
it was very important to me to have some
sense of why I believe the things that I
believed and I couldn't imagine why
anyone wouldn't be deeply concerned with
knowing that yeah yeah people aren't
what are you gonna do right that's not
everyone um so fair enough that's not a
again that's a judgment but likewise
when I do a thing it's important to me
to understand it not just it would never
be good enough for me to be good at a
thing without understanding the
wisenhouse of a thing right
well quick when you're talking about so
like your ear first of all you said when
you said you were most moved by alright
the best acknowledgement you ever had
was by John yeah what are you saying
like you know of anybody you like I I
think I remember you said like you love
better than anyone else I know yeah and
that's like that's that hit at a level
like below vanity that was hit below
like thought that like yeah truth to it
but it also called something deep in you
yeah absolutely
time right and then your menu and you're
talking about and you're talking about
yeah teaching right and I and I I sense
that there's a connection between the
teaching and the love and the way of
course like there's like the knowledge
in the domain of knowledge right and
like knowing that stuff and then and
then is easy to talk about the under
like philosophy for you is like you want
to understand intimately like the things
that you believe right and agree like
it's like a dumbfounded this a little
bit of like why would anybody not like
it just seems to make sense
the quoi is there a connection between
the love and the understanding
uh-uh like I like friendly just sitting
with you just right now I just get this
sense of like when John let like when
you said that obviously I don't know you
know this is like the longest I've
totally but I totally get hit with a
sense of what John's talking about right
and when like tense was that I was hit
with that I don't quite have any you
know I don't quite understand but I just
felt like oh yeah I could get how that's
true and I don't know why and then when
you're talking about like understanding
I was I still had the same sense yeah I
mean why do you make this of my
experience with you so far this is cool
it's I mean look you you you come highly
recommended right John likes you a lot
he speaks very highly of you that's
that's worth a lot to me you know III
don't feel this is quite a naive first
meeting for me maybe I have an undue
advantage because I've gotten to seen
you interact so also though I mean and
this is related to this and I think
that's what John said is intimacy is
easy for me yeah yeah I I connect with
people readily yeah and literally fairly
quickly not everyone you know to you
know my regret should grant an
occasional disadvantage sometimes it
just doesn't work at all well for the
most part I I don't have a problem more
than that ever I find it easy to connect
to people but I think that that comes
it's not an instrumental thing yeah it's
I actually just Jamie like people yeah
looks like that when you said that I was
like admit that makes that makes sense
when you say the intimacy because it's
like oh yeah you just topped on and like
as if as if you in front of each other
for like 10 years or something there's a
there's a in your it seems like in your
just given responsiveness here in
funny it's like I'm not I don't feel
super self-conscious you don't seem at
all self-conscious it's just kind of
like you assumed relatedness that I
found myself inside of with you and with
you such that when you said like oh yeah
love oh why does that make sense but
that's that was I think my greatest
strength as a teacher because that's a
thing you know and again it comes to a
genuine place but I I have a even to
this day I mean I don't actively teach
in a classroom anymore but to this day I
have a profound sense of connection of
fondness of love for my students they're
still in touch with me many of them and
and it's it's I think it's possible to
be a good teacher and not love your
students I imagine that it's possible to
be a like let's say a pure pedagogical
technician I have to counter that's a
possibility right yeah I have no
personal disappearance of that I can't
I also can't imagine other than purely
propositional II like it's I mean the
beauty that the thing about love and
understanding the connection there is
love is the thing that lets you dare to
understand something completely and all
of its flaws because you think without
that powerful orienting motivation
towards a thing right you find out
something about someone or a thing
that's repulsive or repelled or whatever
pushes you away right as a teacher you
need to be unconditionally dedicated
motivated towards your student right
right and teaching is in my view like
there's sort of like two valid non
parasitic non evil intransitive human
relationships that is or non reciprocal
human relationships right where they're
not only not recept
they shouldn't be reciprocal right and
that's parenting and teaching Yeah right
only I am there for my kids my kids have
no reason to be there for me whatsoever
there should never be a situation upon
which I'm relying on them right right
like they need the kids need to be free
to be kids to be growing right there's
no and and likewise with your student
therapy from that not being the case but
this is just it right and and teachers
as well right I mean you need to have
that thing where you are purely there
for them and and there's no I mean it's
lovely when your students appreciate
your the great Fleur that's beautiful
that's lovely I think it's great right
but I've never owned that no one's owed
that no no one should expect that and
it's not a thing that you should get too
comfortable with or about because also
as a teacher you're not someone's friend
much like a parent you were doing your
acting to their best interest at a time
when they are enable uncapable of
grasping their best interest
developmentally right and you proved
your job as as a parent or as a teacher
is your being a prosthetic frame problem
solver right and and so you know Blake
you you have to help get kids along on
those decisions on those choices in
those modes of being that are purely
aspirational there is no rational
step-by-step way that you can say this
is why you should do this or why you
should do like that I've said to
students before I've said look I'm gonna
have to ask you just to take this on
faith like what we're talking about here
is not an amount of smart thing it's a
kind of smarts thing all right you're
about to do something then five years
you're gonna kick yourself in the ass
for right okay I can't provide you a
logical you know if P then Q argument
for this all right I can just tell you
that you were gonna regret this
right yeah I'm asking you please just
take my word for this do this and I feel
gratified that in most cases they listen
okay so if I want to pause right there
so I think we decide to strikes me as
quite profound
right so it's like when you said I can't
proposition allele a out for you right
like and what I heard in that is even if
I could yeah this isn't probably why you
would not want to do it right look
there's something I I'm in I'm present
you here
yeah just gonna have to I'm just ask you
to take it on faith so I'm imagining
what you mean by like love right and
your students right and relating and
your students right in the way just have
a kind of intimacy right that's it's not
it's not a mutual like just same level
in some see there's there's a structure
there right you're not in this eating
things from them but there's a relation
allottee that's just innate for you in
teaching and so crucial and I just got
the sense of like of like for them what
gives them make gives the intelligence
to respond to what you said and to take
in his faith I'm imagine it's very
connected to like the way that you've
related to to them up to that point the
kind of trust sure well I mean what do
you say about that I mean I don't know
because the meet for the most part my
students trust me III I would love to
say this because I'm eminently
trustworthy but that's also so I mean
it's also source free that's weird ASSA
T that's like oh like I'm so hell
radiating the contents of my heart
what's garbage what what I yeah I have
the way I am it has it seems to evoke a
positive response on the occasions where
let's say that faith was tested I've
generally succeeded or have done the
right thing or I've done the appropriate
thing and that works
I mean I'm also gonna say that for all
that I you know I mean I'm someone who's
in most of my academic career has been
around teaching right like I understand
very well how learning works and all of
this stuff but there's also okay sorry
I'm losing my thread a little bit I'm
trying to tie overly ambitious lis I
think a lot of things to guess a lot of
different threads but like I I a couple
of things
I'm sensing what you're talking about in
the way that you are talking about it
sure there's a sense of like you're
already grappling with it right you're
all okay what like in a certain sense
this is what I'm talking your hands and
your moving around and it's funny
because John had mentioned like the way
that you guys work together he's you
know one of the things he says was like
with most people I'm like the one
walking around you know I could totally
like the other people the ones that are
typing or whatever and he says but now
with Leo like Leo especially in the
beginning leaves the ones walking around
and I was like I have a hard time I have
met you yet but now I did sense I really
get that sense of I mean you're just
lucky that I'm confined between this in
the small spaces kids yeah I mean I had
actually contemplated when we were going
to do this before I was thinking I just
do this in the kitchen
and we would do this while I was making
dinner or something because I am very
kinesthetic like I move yeah I do like
my best thinking moving right that's
just that's who I am so yeah I know with
John it is it is funny because John is
an incredibly animated lecturer but but
when John and I or John in the room
think this group was working I'm
inevitably the one pacing around the
table and like you know lunging and
doing all this sort of stuff and
get it engaging in performance arts
that's the part that was gonna say yay
I remembered the phrase and say that for
all that I can talk about the the
technical you know psychological neuro
scientific nature of learning this and
that in the other eye I can also freely
say that a good significant percentage
of successful teaching is performance
art right it's it's how you present
yourself and what you do so and
sometimes it's natural and sometimes
it's calculated
I would for example try and deliberately
to get laughs at certain beats in a
lecture or a lesson because that would
generate more paths back to that insight
so that people have it more accessible
later it's it's not a big deal but it's
something that works right where you
make the moments salient the more that
stuff is accessible for later access and
and and sort of you know you you you
frame it in odd ways you do it like so
so there's a little bit of sort of
stand-up comedy riffing there's all
sorts of stuff but that that performance
aspect is is is is important and I think
that's something that I have a certain
amount of untutored sort of innate
facility with and I don't want to
confuse that with some sort of like
magic empathic bond so I am lucky that I
have a number of features that make me
likable to teenagers
yeah yeah that have nothing to do with
my sincerity with my intentions with my
whatever right right I'm like six foot
three and bald and a relatively
well-built guy I always taught self
defense in hand-to-hand combat as part
of the curriculum so like you know and
and and I have that industry I'm not shy
about the mistakes I've made in my life
or that stuff so there's there's a sense
of connectedness that happens quickly
and these are things that by and large
teenagers respond well to yeah it's not
like that's not magic and it's not
anything even that deep right it's just
a matter of
using what's there like John definitely
has a superpower around teaching because
John is somehow able to communicate his
passion for philosophy to two people
that no one would have any right to
expect would care about it right and and
and he has a tremendously high success
rate at that like it's the he's not
universally beloved per se but no one is
but the rate at which and especially
when you factor in the difficulty
because lots of people can make a
teenage kid like kung fu kung fu is
intrinsically likable to teenage kids
right yeah but but epistemology right I
mean most adults couldn't give a rat's
patoot about epistemology right almost
unfailingly every you know high school
student John has has had their life path
deviated towards philosophy at least to
some degree right that's just that's the
power of his cesareans passion yeah
right I luckily have some parlor tricks
you know that that allow me to be a
reasonably good teacher as well but but
I wanted to be clear about that because
I mean I don't want to confuse I'm going
to conflate two things right I do have I
did have that sincere affection concern
for my kids like I said there's
certainly been instances that have
clearly proven that borne that out I
think it's how certainly the kids
appreciated it but the initial thing if
I have to be honest is mostly charisma
right if some for the general
likeability right right and and I mean
so again not to like also like sprained
my arm patting yourself on the back or
or I'm just trying to be honest with
things basically what you're saying is
like like you know I don't want to like
put off the impression or it's just not
it's not it's not true like like out of
virtue this way
or respects because it's I love the kids
it's there's a way that you're just you
were born this way you have a certain
temperament right this like history and
and it happens to really like work when
it comes to teaching yeah so it's like a
deep some of that stuff isn't
necessarily like a deep thing although
has a deep impact yeah what is the part
for you what is the part for you that is
is is deep is virtuous
what's the what is the part for you that
is like something that like it's a yeah
between you and yourself and your
reality it's like a it's it's something
that you cultivate or or it's not just
given what what is that is it it's what
is that what you say I don't know rame
it that way no no I mean like I mean the
fact is I cultivate all of it at this
point right that's that's that's
something that I mean they feed each
other the sort of let's say Vivi the
understanding and the in the being right
so you know when when when you realize
that the gift you're giving is love
right when you realize that okay so
that's the thing that's the the the
motivational bullet casing that carries
this you learn to be better at it right
realize okay so then right and then you
what does it mean to love well okay
there's these different kinds of love
and there's this and there's the other
right and you formulate your ethic of
non reciprocity yeah right and then you
you go further and you go okay so is
Mareike to go with your first
impressions or do you oh all of these
kids everything you have regardless of
how you feel about them when you first
meet them
right and that's the thing that you have
to go through and you go okay all right
you know so maybe person X isn't as
immediately likable it was what was that
like what was it like going through it
like going through that in
coming to that like was it was it like
you feel like what was it like for you
like I said you feel bad for the people
you may have let down in the past you
try harder to be that much better for
the people in your future and yeah do I
mean there's this idea that that love is
masterless it's just this thing yeah
it's this force and we just it's fruit
listen to anything other than submit to
it to try and stand it's a mistake to
try and bend it or shape it's a mistake
and and I think that's one of the most
hurtful things we've internalized as a
culture I think that we owe it to
ourselves so love as well as we can and
in fact I think it's kind of a it's
becoming a matter of survival dude I
mean like the way that we all feel
differently about things in the way that
we find these isolated nodes that are so
set against each other and it's like
it's not the disagreements fun really
bad quite the opposite disagreements
essential also for growth and
development other processing is
everything without that there is no
development there is no growth it's the
opponent processing is the mathematical
engine that drives complexification that
allows for growth development and
expansion of capacity and capability but
but that at opponents he has to happen
in some neutral framework there has to
be some machinery keeping it together
otherwise it all flies apart right right
yeah and and so I mean as we get to the
point where our intellect becomes an
increasingly terrifying force multiplier
with the consequences of the game of
human interaction grow so much it
becomes that much more important to
recognize that you have to ground things
and love that love is that
love is the medium that keeps these
things together it's the part where you
you can even allows you to to ignore
evidence it allows you to ignore things
that are pushing you away from someone
to go know they're still with me yes
right and you say you're saying it's
like what I'm hearing I'm hearing the
virtuous like I'm hearing I'm hearing
the love is is both I'm hearing it as is
both a virtue
right you know that would cause me to
have the virtue yes yes yeah yeah no
that that seems good I mean I I I'm
riffing here and and the beauty of this
sort of interaction is is that I mean I
haven't I don't think I've said many of
these words before even Express Express
with these propositions before like this
is yeah boats by the conversations way
and like really like the sort of thing
because I do it's how you how you
excavate yourself right is how it's how
you take what you haven't you Minh of
course right things that are in your
head you think or says a little but
they're not yeah anyone who was thought
they were profound while they were
smashed on something and has written
down can tell you house how Lane just
being yourself is you know I need to do
it on your own like utter nonsense you
like oh my lord
like cretin right but somehow when you
talk to someone you're in genius it's
amazing like all this stuff right like
the what the gods he was talking about
right like when I mean Vygotsky thought
of intelligence in a number of different
ways and and and there was certainly
there was the G the internal this right
but there's a way in which there's a
synergy and people interacting that's
different and I'm not talking about
Gardner's multiple intelligences in
they're talking about interpersonal
intelligence I'm talking about the
synergy of a dynamical system of
opponent-process because even though
there were of like minds in the sense
that we're both predisposed to having
this conversation right what's making
this move is the opponent see you
the others right not just that were
others you're provoking right like you
know you're asking a question and you're
asking and you're aiming them right
you're aiming them for my mitt right
yeah like it's in and so when that's
done skillfully that's the Socratic
method is right right because then you
don't just move someone to the right for
no reason right what you do is you move
them in a way that suddenly they realize
the value of this or that Li it's you
you you try to create it's not good
enough to create aporia right you have
to create them at critical spaces you
have to create it
where insights provoked yes yes that's
the skill in being a good interlocutor
that's where you know again in throwing
it right not just there are some dance
like a monkey to lead it somewhere right
I'm sensing the mid with three part of
it like there's a there's a quality
because for me it's like there it's a
cottage so it's got so much like doing
this for what circling that there's a
lot of like really really deeply getting
people they have no Socratic circles and
coming around to it it's funny it's more
like I think as time has gone on the
thing that doing that like over and over
and over again has I think you're right
it's there is a there is a quality love
about it
that is that is that does it calls me
will go where else would you do it yeah
but those moments of those like those
key moments that you're talking about of
like timing and and the right like the
right pressure and the right like
opposition or the right space that whole
thing it is I've really appreciated like
like understanding more of like
listening as mid with right this kind of
quality of like a like a midwife is the
different you know people get midwives
right and I'll never forget this because
I've been in tubers my son's birth and
then one of my best friends at the times
birth and she had a midwife and then she
had to go to the hospital and he was so
clear that what in Midwood weren't with
us to the hospital midwife was still mid
withering as the birth at the hospital
was happening but it wasn't what the
doctors were doing no and I think what
was what what that difference was is
that she was becoming impregnated in a
certain sense with the with with the
process and kind of like being
impregnated with the birthing baby right
in a certain sense she became the rule
right in that like to receive the baby
to then turn it like give it back to the
to the mother that woman that kind of
spacious proactive vulnerability that
like kind of like staying it edge of
something all of it is does you know
it's funny now that you're talking about
it it does feel like that that is deeply
revealed and Tommy I love what that's
that's that's just it right I mean if
you because it's not just so just the
doing right not just the questions the
listening is the spaces you create the
affordances right the way you shape that
space is as important as the
provocations you make right
I am we were lucky in that my wife chose
to have a midwife and we have a very
good Midwife for my last child and a
doula right
doula got your Midwife and I if it's a
dual in a midwife do the Midwife does a
lot more of the quasi medical stuff okay
like in in the the Midwife is concerned
a lot with the baby right the dual is
more concerned with the woman's
experience of pregnancy and pregnancy in
and that like wiki that after cuz
[Laughter]
I'm just giving you my best sense of
this right but one thing that I've
learned about myself is I have a very
authoritative way of speaking and and
and and people often want to believe
what I say and often take what I say
seriously and and and I am so stupid no
it should take me just saying that
sometimes I go and by the way you know
like wiki that if I haven't
provided you the citation go check for
sources yeah but I
I mean I'm a skeptical person and I'm
not like I'm not one of these like jerk
online skeptics who are like out to get
some sort of like ego stroked by by
dropping a ton of logical fallacies in
someone's head I just I care about my
epistemic hygiene and yeah and and and
as I said I like to know why I believe
things yeah right so that and and and
again and and and it's it's troubling to
me like you know the the sort of both
the lack of criticism people bring to
bear and and the absurd criticism people
bring to bear only people seem to be
only capable people I often see you know
the extreme the extreme sort of warped
versions of criticism and skepticism and
not enough like a useful one right so I
was you know I will admit to having not
had a very strongly a very positive
notion or thought of you know feeling
for midwives right midwife came over for
an appointment which already put her in
my good books right like it made my
wife's life easier she came over and we
had a conversation and the woman's
knowledge is encyclopedic she's in
brilliant oh crap
okay you win you know what you like
let's go right the duel is well like
these were these were like learning
intelligent thoughtful people I have no
reservations anymore after that right
and especially being there and in and in
see how utterly ineffectual my presence
was at the birth did I mean like my wife
could hold my hands come ahead I was
there for her right but I lacked the
kind of love that you have for your wife
is different than the love the Midwife
has for your wife okay and and the
Midwife can love your wife through the
most horrible pain do you know and and
love your wife in a way this is no you
got to feel us wait a bit longer you can
do this right and I'm a blubbering pile
of and I'm willing to jump out the
window to end my life suffering do you
[Laughter]
know I mean that's that's something you
don't have to wiki we could just take
that as I like its it you you realize
that right but again it comes down to
love like that's you you can't be a
midwife or the loving that person I mean
not liking them you can dislike them
immensely yeah the beautiful thing about
love you can dislike the I don't
whoever it is that you love right just
to love them right right and and that's
and that's important it's important to
keep these things right and you still
have that that that ability right to
maintain a powerful motivational
framework oriented towards that person's
greater good right no matter what
yeah totally it's um you know I I mean
it it also helped me mediate with the
kids themselves more than once right I
mean you've got a kid who's not doing
well with the other kids and there's
some you know bullying you know are
about to be bullying in a slanty can be
frank it's like just you know you can
help this kid integrate you can also
help these kids were being jerks to not
be jerks the important thing is to
realize as unlikable as bullying is as
as viscerally yes viewing as it is right
when it's kids doing it you don't owe
them moral judgment you owe them
teaching because they're kids because of
course they're not doing it right
because kids don't do anything right
kids and what I'm kind of like it's
funny as you're walking like on some
level this is just like it's kind of it
strikes it's like people I can't imagine
people say like oh yeah of course it's
obvious so that's what you do well what
that what I as you've been walking
through it I've been I was struck I
found myself in in the observation of
the switch from like you know you don't
make them wrong you know like you know
you aren't disgusted with them no you
see like there's something about there's
something a place that you're holding as
a teacher right that that not only just
knows that their kids therefore they
need to learn but like I'm some of I saw
myself as you're describing it and
listening to you I saw myself seeing
like a future and the kids something
that's transcendent in the kid that they
can't know about but I can actually see
and I would imagine my degree of being
able to see that right yeah is a is it
is through is part of the thing that
grows you as a teacher I would imagine
Oh things that is evident that you're
growing as a teacher is like you're not
like just tolerating them and then
remembering that they're just kids it's
like no you see them bullying and then
but you also see this possibility within
them and are able to like
relate to the bullying and that frame
all in what's like see the person you
see their future self in parallel yeah
right you're rescuing their future self
you're doing the same way the same way
that you can improve your ability to
instill for example healthy habits
yourself so the way that you one of the
techniques that allows you to combat
temptation in the moment yeah right is
to create a personal relationship
between you today and you in the future
right - literally engage in the exercise
of creating in your head there's future
me and having a conversation
instantiating a model of yourself and
having a conversation allowing yourself
to love that person and to feel
responsibility for them right and it's
just as important to go back as future
you and thank yourself right and you
create you remember to yourself you go
thank you for that you know creating
that personal relationship is one of the
things that lets you transcend
hyperbolic discounting and stuff like
that that lets you offset all the things
that allow bad habits right right you
don't just have to do that with yourself
you can do that with anyone yeah right
though you don't just feel like your
student isn't this kid now right this is
a life right this is a future this is a
parent this is this is everything right
there's a universe of possibilities that
you have a hand in shaping right and and
of course you know like so because in
the moment we can all be hideously
unlikable right you obviously you can't
rely on that right that's empty right so
of course you you create those models
not just to the person in but who are
they gonna be what are they you know
like and and of course this behavior
that makes it so much easier to see that
for what it is don't get me wrong you
don't you can't help everyone you don't
connect with everyone it's not perfect
some people are well beyond your ability
to affect some people some kids who
bully are destined to be monsters right
but you know what they've got plenty of
time to be monsters you can do your best
now huh right right you'll do your best
now yeah I'll just say I'm just really
appreciating what you're saying I've
been quite an experience just keep
talking about this and what's kind of
coming to light for me yeah
I think which is often the case in these
kinds of conversations right is uh it's
funny because it's a poking a sense of
like affinity and love for you and like
like but also this sense of sorry just
yeah
giving my wife some paper this sense of
I I've been really fortunate to have a
number of teachers throughout my life
since I was a kid yeah I kind of come
from like you know an addictive family
background and a lot of things that come
with that but I had a grandfather who
was like this wise old awesome right
that would tell me story after story
after story that in some way I feel like
him
that is why paper oh goodness me that is
blowing paper my apologies sorry there
we go
I had foolishly provided light paper
instead of plain white paper and the
lighting is such that it was difficult
to tell ah all right
I'm yours again
sorry yeah totally III think I was just
having this experience of like as you
were which is often the case I've
noticed like within sites is one it
seems to evoke this quality of insight
has this quality of this it has love
involved right that just seems part of
the experience like insights like whoa
and then it I notice it I get a new
history option right like like I go I'm
going back right now and I'm just I'm
recalibrating if you sorry seeing that
all of the men and women in my life that
just kind of in a certain sense under
the wing like hearing us talk about like
Oh being able to see right like this is
part of the of the love I'm imagining
this is like I know we can talk about
this too but like the notion like the
distinction of copy right here but being
able to see I'm just seeing more clearly
like that that like seeing it's not just
seeing me now it's seeing me the
potential of me in the future the past
right like it's deeply relevant right
because what happened to you in the past
is is has everything to do with what
you're doing now right and what you're
doing now goes into who you'll be in the
future but no one moment the beauty of
it is no one moment is defining or
damning dude I mean yeah it's like yes
there's this this weird pervasive
transience the whole thing when you let
go of this sort of weird Cartesian need
for an unchanging persistent core right
you let that go you realize that you can
be whatever I mean like I it's very
freeing yeah but it's free in so many
ways because then you don't need to like
when you can let go that essentialism
right it makes it easier to both to love
and to be lovable yeah right right
because
hey you know like serious antipathy
becomes like trying to like hold you
know sand in your fists right as Leah
says Aveda right or we'll slip through
your fingers right it's just you can
just it's I always felt that beauty
couldn't exist without impermanence that
impermanence is an essential piece of a
thing being beautiful it has to end in
some way right that that's what we are
it's great because who we are moments a
moment is different right this you right
now is gone and gone forever
yeah the beauty is like Jesus it I've
always noticed about Beauty just have
it's like like really intense beauty
it's like you feel into it has a quality
or a tinge of sadness yeah yeah
absolutely absolutely and it's an
important lesson to learn I mean to
think that again beauty's misunderstood
in our culture and the way again it's
it's beauty is a thing that we attribute
to objects or even to people in a very
superficial way that has that that's
this mistaken
like what again it sort of phrase that
John used once that I released step with
no should be tempted by the good right
it's a great thing a person yes this but
for me like I said you know specifically
is attempted by the good because it's a
wonderful thing is temptation were
always we always automatically we
temptation is being pulled towards doing
something wrong right it's a temptation
if the the goal of the act or the
acquisition isn't in some way bad right
yeah
is it but why why does that have to be
right what is it like there's nothing
intrinsic to the Mars bar
it doesn't radiate temptones quantum
business there's like
must eat Mars bar right everything
tracks me to the Mars bar is in my head
yeah yeah absolutely everything is in my
head right for that so you know beauty
is in our heads right which means we own
it which is responsible for it yes yes
and so well you don't go around
castigating people for not having I
don't know not finding person or thing X
waiters that specifically beautiful
right there's a sense in which we owe it
to ourselves to cultivate our sense of
beauty the aesthetics is a woefully
ill-treated yeah discipline like when
they say the true the good and the
beautiful right as these hurdles under
say they're meant to be links but those
are it to be educated yes right you have
to be able to discern the truth yes
right truth isn't just doesn't just
deliver itself to you anything gets
delivered truth is garbage right it's so
sort of sell you something yeah if
there's a there is no truth right truth
must be discerned go right yeah and the
truth helps you realize what is good
yeah right and if you do things right
beauty helps you because you find the
good beautiful yes right you learn to
find the good beautiful is how you
become tempted by the good right
and then truth beauty and good it's like
in a sense of like what salient of the
mark like it's it's like it has this
thing that they were talking about
before which is yeah when I'm able to
look at my student and really see the
student to be a teacher right is to see
not just the student in front of me not
just the act that they did but like to
see more like horizons of temporal like
temporality they give the ground and
being able to respond to it so it's like
with the Mars bar the Mars block is only
like beautiful to the degree what I
don't include like the sugar crash and
how fat I'll get from it and like all of
the craving and oh if I if I don't see
that right Mars bar will crave but if I
do see that right it becomes less
beautiful less beautiful and therefore
what it's like it becomes less salient
to me yeah and you can make other things
beautiful like I mean people used to
study music appreciation yeah think
about that for a second right because
I'm one you know you can't teach that
it's yes you can yeah you learn yeah we
don't do enough of that that's not an
important enough piece of our education
we allow domain-specific experts develop
appreciation right like there's music
for musicians right I love music for
musicians
that's so illuminating that stuff okay
so when I was growing up I had a bunch
of friends who were really new guitar
yeah I can't carry a tune in a bucket
and I mean I played a quarterly made for
like every other kid in my with you know
in my context and and but I'm not a
musician by any stretch but I love music
and like I said I had a bunch of fun
twenty guitar and I ended up listening
to a bunch of bands and musicians who
were not widely appreciated let's say
well someday they were they were music
for musicians it's fantastic and stuff
and I mean some of its fan more mates
for success but I mean so like if you're
a guitar player right well at least back
in my day which is we won't give a
specific date because that would just be
shameful and embarrassing you know
anyway mom Osteen was like a big deal
right
Swedish guitar player who you know could
play twenty three notes per second I
could just shred like crazy right
you know joe satriani who actually says
that it goes in the g3 tour every day is
is it very successful he's seen a much
more sort of broader audience you know
Steve Vai who's was more successful but
also is absolutely
musician right right I I feel I see that
and I had this tiny waiting like wow we
should all have this we should all be
able to see this all right yeah you know
inevitably I get to our players gonna
appreciate guitar differently than me I
get that right but I can certainly get
close right I can get closer to that
cultivation cultivating our aesthetic
sensibilities is an important skill
right both for enjoying our lives for
appreciation but also I think it like
deeply crucial because that is how you
know that is how we can bring beauty
back into the the true the good picture
right otherwise it's a pretty Spartan
not cool thing right I mean it's it's
without the beauty part we're creating
like the Spock fallacy right this idea
that you know we can either enjoy our
lives or we can like be dedicated to
truth right and it's like that's garbage
like that's that's just silly it's I
mean it's just it's not true in any
sense of it but it's it's this cartoon
of wisdoms cartoon of rationality that
sort of pervade that people like and
it's and it feeds the worst part of us I
guess the problem right it it's it's it
it bombs a hurt that people feel about
not being included about this or
whatever but it doesn't balm it by
bringing them back in but by helping
them connect but by justifying their
separation dude I mean I see you are
right you are better than they are right
right right
it's pornography right I mean that's
kind of what pornography is right it's
got nothing specific to do with with
lurid sex or whatever it's it's getting
that cheap gratification without having
earned having gone through having right
right it's the rewarding of our basest
impulses it kind of like it
it requires the
like the giving up of agency or
sovereignty and in the act I think what
wasn't it wasn't it James Joyce had a
lot to say about this um
that sense of we're talking about I
think it was Joyce it was talking about
the difference between like pornography
right right
and fine fine art and he said like fine
art fine it's something about about
something really artful is it it seems
to create this this this basic question
right that that isn't immediately
intelligible but draws in a mutual
intelligently right that that would oaks
evokes to participation whereas with and
I think Weber was it that the
sociologist Weber who do then kind of
took that and he this is where he
thought television was dangerous yeah as
it removes he his thought was it removes
that space of reflection yeah
you literally get taken on this ride
right yeah it's and then you get taken
off and there's no you just you didn't
have any of that kind of sense of having
to grapple and articulate and to see and
to struggle right there's no reaching
yeah it's like being spoon-fed right
yeah totally you know so here's a meal
that you then can you eat right if here
you go right every bite for you
everything just hey deliver to you
there's no effort there's no nothing it
just pure sensation yes
since void of perception yes right I
mean this is like a joke I talk about
confirmation porn right like the way in
which you know we love to read things
that tell us what we know already I make
it a point for example like if you're
reading something and if if you're not
disagreeing with it
all right or learning something for the
first time then you're wasting your time